{
  "reference_number": "2583",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "otherwise the commission will be merely today's tokenism that will soon be a sidelined office somewhere in the commission industry"
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "R&D Also consultation with Maoridom"
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Also to comment on whether trading schemes are effective or just shuffling the deck and that maybe carbon tax is the way to go."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "You would think scientists would be employed not old party hacks."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "One issue is to avoid, the other is adaption. So looking at two issues. Adaption is so complex according to region that response\ninvolves Regional Councils. However, some District Councils are so useless it might require a national response if regions fail. Take\nThames Coromandel District Council, they are still draining coastal wetland reserves for the benefit of surrounding pasture . However\n\nif Government can't monitor the Reserves Act how are they going to respond to blatant detrimental treatment of carbon sinks? How is\nthe Act going to be different form a fat policy document that doesn't give regulatory roles?"
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Advising is all very good but for large emitters and councils there should be mandatory reporting. But then there is the issue of the\n\nquality of those reports."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Refrigerants - New Zealand’s Climate Denial. Small amounts but significant due to potency. Example of legislation nobody paying\n\nattention to. If we are to reduce greenhouse gases why in NZ so poor on refrigerants? The irony of people wringing their hands over\nemissions yet nobody seems concerned over the fridge unless it fails to keep the chardy cool. When it fails the fridge is dumped,\n\ngases released. Yes, yes there is a law that says such gases are not to be released into the atmosphere but like so many\nenvironmental laws in NZ, few pay attention. (Even councils regularly flout the Reserves Act.) For if there is no enforcement it is as\n\ngood as no law at all. So let’s forget about announcing the edicts that cause no change and actually figure out a way to stop\nrefrigerants being released from discarded fridges, air conditioning units, dehumidifiers, heat pumps etc At present companies that\nrun transfer stations allow the dumping of fridges into scrap metal piles. They ask that they are dumped on condition that they have\n\nbeen ‘de-gassed’. For a start that is not always checked and if it is, and found intact, the dumper is asked to de-gas. The most\ncommon response is the dumper to simply cut the refrigerant line. The company running the transfer station then can claim it is the\n\nresponsibility of the dumper and wash their hands but it results in the same thing. It is free to dump a fridge as the metal is recycled.\nThe dump operator gets free metal out of the deal. Fridges make up a very large proportion of that scrap metal pile. Perhaps the\n\nanswer is to require transfer station operators to have a role in recycling the gases and for the polluter to pay. To dump a fridge with\ngas will cost something to recover that gas but it should cost significantly more to dump a fridge with the refrigerant line cut. Yes,\nthere are refrigeration companies that de-gas fridges but it has been known that people pay for such a service only to discover the\n\ncompany has simply snipped the line out of convenience. All fridges etc end up at the dump so why not concentrate recovery there?\nHow to get transfer station operators, that to me seem very disinterested in recycling, to carry out recovery? The pit seems cheaper\n\nand more convenient for so much waste. I fear it might have to be a case of forcing operators to have a system in place that can\neasily be monitored and audited if they want fridge metal. Will this result in them not accepting items at all and promote fly tipping?\nLeast then it will be an issue that is open as opposed to what exists in NZ now which is a total denial. I brought a dehumidifier the\n\nother day but nowhere on the machine or in the manual did it list the refrigerant. So obviously the manufacturer doesn’t even think\nthe gas will be recycled. The store selling me the dehumidifier had no idea. An end of life recovery bounty system financed at the\n\npoint of sale would have worked here. But we really don’t care. We say we do, but it’s like buying a plastic dolphin to show how much\nyou care about the sea. There is a connection in people’s head but not in reality. Fridge dumping really does seem an issue we have\n\nseriously overlooked in the plethora of Climate Change mission statements. I look forward to the day NZ gets real on hazardous\nmaterials (well behind the OECD on that) and actually monitors what we are doing as a country. Choosing to take a bag to the\nsupermarket is not going to do it. Please consider gases used in rolling out more heat pumps etc. What is the end point?"
    }
  ]
}
